[Music]
hello and welcome to Auto X my name is
Kar Maur and you find me in the heart of
South Delhi staring at a
thousand-year-old wall and I will be
honest with you we were supposed to be
in a dreamy location somewhere filming a
proper travel log but while doing the
research for that I found myself
pondering upon a question I'm a
millennial and I'm a foreign breed
Delite so what places does Deli have to
hold which show the significance of why
it became the capital of our country and
today I'm going to take you through the
top five places spread across multiple
generations and thousands of years apart
which show the timeline of how deadly
progressed and why it is the great
capital of our country so without
further Ado let's get started we have
many places to go and lots of things to
show
you
so if you guys have read the Mahabharata
you would have heard accounts of the
city of Indra prast it was India's first
smart city and established under the
Kuru Kingdom it was also mentioned in
Buddhist text and under scriptures
during ashoka's Reign but scientists
pinpoint its location some where around
the panaka area but there is no evidence
to prove that fact so if proven history
is to be believed around the 11th
century ad under ages of an Singh Tomar
of Tomar Dynasty he established the L
Cod this was the original Red Fort and
had nothing to do with the red Fort
built by Shah jaha 500 years later this
was the beginning stages of the
fortification of Delhi and really served
as an important figure in the timeline
of the delhi sulate now today not lot
remains of course it was a magnificent
site when it was built it had a
circumference of 2 mil wide with walls
about 30 ft wide and today it is a
protected Monument under the
archaeological Survey of India not a lot
remains but if you come to this location
you'd be able to see the remains of the
fort and you also have the kar complex
not far away you have shops of Interest
selling cultural items and lots of local
Delicacies serving around the place so
as your first place of visit kilar P or
LOD should be on your list to
[Music]
do now from killer R petora we now move
500 years in the future to 1648 at that
was the time when Shah jaha moved his
capital from Agra to Delhi and to
commemorate that occasion he built this
L Killa or red
[Music]
[Applause]
f
[Music]
[Applause]
this was built as a fortified wall
around the city of shahan Abad which is
now known as old Delhi it was built in
red and white which is shahan's favorite
color and its architect is ustad Ahmed
Lori who coincidently was also the
architect for Taj Mahal now it wasn't
just important for the British Raj but
in 1948 javahar Neu the first Prime
Minister of India also delivered his
first speech to the country right from
these walls this is quite important and
also established Delhi as the
administrative capital of India at that
time so now we move further to the
British Raj and go to a place called
coronation Park which is also
significantly important for the timeline
of
Delhi
[Music]
[Applause]
from the Red Fort we now move about 250
years ahead in time and where I am is
coordination Park in delhi now the
English imitated the traditions of Hindu
and Muslims of getting the people
together and this exact place was the
spot of the first Darbar now that was
initiated by Lord lighton and done in
order to commemorate the coronation of
Queen Elizabeth as the Empress of India
now this not only held significant
importance to the British but also was
significant to show the importance of
the mobile
[Music]
Empire Today the coronation Park holds
less significance in Heritage but is
more of a place of leisure and
entertainment for the people who live
around the park and with that now we've
moved from the British Raj all the way
up to our economic liberalization and
see what part Delhi held in that aspect
of the Indian
history
[Music]
[Applause]
Now we move past 1947 and India's
independence now this was a time of
economic liberalization there were many
reforms which resulted in an absolute
Boom for the country and you have places
like this Han market now this turned
into commercial hub sport in the 1990s
you was start started in 1951 and
consisted of 154 shops 71 residences
which were given as seed land to
immigrants from the Northwest Frontier
now today this serves as a melting port
for the old and the new and it's quite a
popular destination for tourists and
natives alike along with that you also
have places like the Indian habitat
Center which serve as convention centers
for people to get together and serve as
a commercial hub sport for the young and
upcoming
[Music]
so you finally find me in present day
and none of it is represented better
than a place like gurugram popularized
by delhi's growing young population and
multinational companies to set up shop
well just look at around you it's
bustling it's magical and full of energy
now you find me at a place called
cyberhub which is a sprawling hub for
shopping food bars and everything that
represents a growing India and
surrounded by modern offices and
Residences I feel cyberhub is the
perfect place to end our journey in
tracing delhi's timeline but if you
think gurug Graham is a new addition to
the map well here's an interesting story
gurug Graham was also set to be the
birth place of gurara who was in fact
the teacher to the coras and pandas
which we mentioned first in our premal
period so ladies and gentlemen that was
our journey across top five places which
represent why Delhi is the
administrative capital of India why it
is important and all the mix of old new
culture Heritage and everything which
makes this city great so as you guys can
see Delhi and his name in districts have
always been steeped in history and never
did lose in importance and it has also
grown into the Metropolis that you see
today so ladies and gentlemen that was
the end of my video I hope you like this
one and if you did please do hit the
like button and tell us in the comment
section down below what you think of
Delhi what you think of its people of
its places and everything that it
represents thank you for watching my
name is k Maur I'll see you guys
later
[Music]
w